Guys Shandra said welcome to concept and
coding and today we are going to do JWT
implementation in a springboard. So very
very important part and let's see that
we will go in depth and clear each and
every part of it. So let's start without
wasting any time. So from the previous
video this one we have already
understood what is JWT. It's a stateless
authentication method. Stateless. You we
already know that server do not maintain
the user authentication state. No
session is maintained at server side and
it has three part. JWT has three part
header, payload and signature. We have
already seen that each part in depth in
the previous video. But for a quick
overview, first part is header which is
kind of a meta data like what algorithm
we are using for signing purpose,
signature purpose. Okay, so this is just
like what algo we are used. Second is
payload. This is the data which actually
holds some info specific to application.
Let's say that I am uh putting subject
ID, some ID, user ID or username or
something expiry time, email, right? Uh
issuer. So all these details and I have
already explained you different types of
payload also. Sometime it is also known
as claims, right? So we have private
claim, public claim. So there are
different type of claim which we have
already seen in this video. Okay? So for
now we know that in the payload we store
some data which application uses it. And
the third part is signature. The
signature part is
that where we are using the algorithm
whatever we have specified in the header
right and we sign the payload. Okay. So
it ensures token integrity prevents
tempering any change in payload like
somebody has changed the role from user
to admin. So when we will recalculate or
verify verify the signature right that
will not match. So this responsibility
is that the integrity maintenance of the
payload no changes should have happened.
So that we have seen. So once we are and
also that u all three parts are divided
by
this dot. Okay. So part one, part two,
part three like this header, payload and
signature. Okay. And this is the sample
token which we have seen like this is
first part is header. Second part is
your payload. This is nothing but a base
form. Okay. This is also base 64 form.
Okay. and third one is your
signature. So till now here we are clear
about the what is JWT and its structure.
Okay, if you have not seen the previous
video kindly have a look then uh it
would be much
clear. Now what steps we have to follow
to implement it? So first step we will
follow is definitely user creation. So
we will expose one API API/ user-
register through which we will create a
user in our DB. Okay, that would be our
first step and we have already seen that
in the previous video. I think second
part of the security is that only user
creation part. So once the user is
created what we have to do, we have to
generate a token. Okay. So here if you
see the first step
is user creation. So in our DB we have
now user user one and password let's say
1 2 3. So that is done. After that we
have a token generation means they call
something like let's say we will expose
API generate token
API generate token API in that they will
pass the username and password U1 and
password 1 2 3. So they will pass it. So
here we will do
matching matching with the DB and if
it's all good we will return a
token JWT token. So this is our the
second step which we have to do. The
third one is token validation. In that
one what we will do
is now user got the token they have to
access any resource let's say / users or
any restricted resource they will pass
the JWT token to the server okay so it
will
validate the
token okay if the token is valid it will
be like allowed the uh access to the
resource is allowed out. Okay. If not,
it will throw an
exception. The last one is refresh
token. So sometime what happen is this
token is got expired. So there can we we
can expose one API / refresh
token / refresh token through which we
will
validate the
refresh
token and we will generate a
new access
token.
Okay. So we need to provide the
functionality to the user to refresh its
JWT token. Sometime what happen is this
token right which has been generated
okay in the step two they have a short
live period generally 5 minutes or 10
minutes right so they expired very soon
so after 5 minutes again user should not
provide its username password so
generally in parallel refresh token is
also sent to the client they can use
that refresh token to generate a new
access token okay so all this
functionality we have to
Okay. So we will go step by step. The
first step is user creation dynamically.
And again I have already explained how
to create a user dynamically in this
video. Username and password creation
part. Okay. So this is the
implementation. Okay. But I have already
explained this. So I will not go again
into this one. How to create a user. So
kindly uh take a reference of this video
and the first part we can easily do that
we have already seen that in the
previous part video. Okay. So just uh
like we have created a user controller
where I have exposed this user register
API. Okay. And uh we have user register
entity where we have username password
role. User will pass it. We will encode
it. we will um hash the password and we
will store it save in the DB. Okay. And
we also have to uh implement this user
detail service. I have already told the
reason why right because this we have to
implement this override this method and
we have to tell to the spring boot how
to fetch the data from the DB because
spring boot doesn't know what table and
all. So that's why we have to implement
user detail service this we have already
seen. So at the part of
this once we done that from API if we
hit this / API/ user register and give
username is sj password is 1 2 3 role is
ro user user is registered successfully
message we will get and if we see the db
we will see that one table got added
user_register this is what the entity
which we have created right this is the
entity which we have
created and we have this ID password
role username got added and password is
in the hashed form so that's what we are
doing right we are creating the hash
first and then saving
it so I am hoping that you have already
gone through this video so you already
know that how to create a user
dynamically
Okay. So that first part is done. Now
here comes the important part and now
from here we have to understand things
much clearly and better. Token
generation. So now see
that spring boot do not provide any
default implementation for JWT
authentication. So if you remember from
form based or basic
authentication have we code anything?
No. Framework has all the things ready
for us. Okay. We just have to tell into
uh spring uh security config what
authentication we have to use and that's
all. Everything is handled by the
framework
itself. But for JWT there is no such
implementation. Right? Why? You can ask
why? Because see for JWT different
applications have different requirement.
What data you have to put in payload
could be different right? What signing
algorithm you have to use? What are the
refreshing strategy? Some might not need
it, some need it, right? So how much
time uh this refresh token is valid or
not. So requirement is very different
for different different application. So
that's what spring bootut says that hey
I have already have a
framework you can go and enhance for the
JWT authentication but in simple terms
the onus comes to engineer now to
implement the JWT functionality we have
to implement the JWT
functionality and that's why there is no
one solution for it different engineers
different ways to implement it
so if you see different resources you
will see that hey somebody has
implemented in this way somebody has
implemented in this way so don't get
confused because since spring boot has
not provided the implementation we
engineers are implementing it by own so
definitely knows one solution would be
there different engineer different ways
to implement so what we will stick to I
will try to stick to security framework
itself we will take the advantage of the
spring boot security framework network
itself and we will try to implement the
JWT functionality. We will not create
any resource like generate
token or uh refresh token something into
the
controller. We will not use controller.
Controller is I will say that put our
business
logic security related we have a
security framework and security
framework has given us what do you mean
by framework framework is something
which you can build on top of it right
so definitely we can expand the
functionality we can add new
functionality of JWT on the existing
security framework that's what we will
try to do and for that let me give you
one quick recap of architecture and from
this recap I will tell you one thing
which we have to notice which will help
us to do this enhancement okay so don't
skip this this is very important part
like you might say that hey I already
know the architecture but here I'm going
to tell you one thing which we have to
note is very
important in this flow which help us to
enhance this
functionality so we already know that
when the request comes in what would
happen. The first part happen is
security filter got invoked. So now the
security filter chain got invoked. The
request goes to the filter chain.
Correct? There are multiple filter
chain. Let's say any one of the filter
got invoked. As we seen that right in
form based one of the filter get invoked
in basic authentication another filter
get invoked. So now let's say that any
one of the filter get invoked. What they
will do? See this very important they
create authentication object we have
seen that okay like
uh in form based what filter got invoked
username password
filter they create an object of I think
username password token this is the
authentication so authentication is an
interface and these are all its
implementation username
password token and in the basic
authentication there is something called
basic uh authentication filter and they
might have generated their own token
right uh something basic token something
so what I'm trying to say that each
filter creates their own authentication
object very important just keep it in
your head for now because we are going
to come back to this Again now this
filter pass this authentication object
to the authentication manager which is
an interface and this is the
implementation of it. Now what it will
do provider manager provider manager
delegate this request which is coming to
one of the authentication provider.
There are many authentication provider
DAO authentication provider different
different authentication provider. So
one of the authentication
provider will receive this
authentication object and who will pass
it? Provider manager will pass it. Okay.
Again concentrate on
this delegate. So provider manager is
the one which delegate the request and
how it delegate we will see that because
this is going to help us to enhance the
functionality and once the provider
receives the request they will performs
the operation what they are intend to do
and then they return back the fully
authentication response. Yes,
authenticated is true. I am able to
match the uh I am able to authenticate
the user and ultimately it return the
object back to the filter and the filter
stored it into the security context
holder depend upon the authentication
meth method.
Right? So this is the basic flow which
we have seen till now. But now notice
one behavior very important behavior.
First security filter is the one which
creates authentication object.
Okay, which with data coming from
request like username, password or
session ID or token. So when the request
comes in, they will pass either
username, password or session ID or
let's say JWT token and ultimately with
this data filter get invoked and with
that data itself it will create an
authentication object. So this is be
clear. Okay. So here at this point of
time authentication object has uh like
the details which user has passed either
username password or session ID or token
but authentication is false
currently correct but does it know which
authentication provider can handle it?
Does it know that at this security
filter knows that hey my this object
should goes to this provider or this
provider. Does it know? No. Who knows
it? Provider manager knows it.
Authentication manager. So that is the
authentication manager. Provider manager
is nothing but an authentication
manager. So authentication manager has a
list of authentication providers. It has
a list. It calls support method of each
authentication provider. So what happen
is this provider manager has a list of
authentication
provider. Okay. And it iterate over each
provider and each provider has something
called support method.
Support
support. So it it calls each provider
and calls their support method and check
hey I am getting this authentication
object. Can you handle it? Can you
support it? Any one of them which says
yes this delegate the request to that
provider. Okay. So authentication
manager has a list of authentication
provider. It calls support method of
each authentication provider and pass
the authentication object and check if
they can handle it or not. Okay. So it
call support method and pass this
authentication authentication object and
check hey can you handle it any of the
provider which says yes it will pass it
to delegate it to that
provider. So let's see the framework
provider manager framework. So we can
see this functionality from here. So it
iterate over a list of providers. Okay.
So here here if you see it has a for
loop. It has a for loop iterating over
the list of providers. Okay. From this
list of provider it is calling
support. Okay. It is calling support
method for each provider and checking
hey can you handle it? If no it will
continue go to the next provider and
check can you support it. Any one of
them say that yes I can support it. It
will call its
authenticate method. Hey now you go
ahead
unauthenticated. We have to use the same
functionality
to implement JWT.
How? See that we need to enhance this
functionality itself for JWT. Now just
see this colored one. Focus on this
colored one. If we have to enhance the
JWT what we have to do let's say request
comes with data let's say
token security filter pass it to the
chain so one thing first we have to do
right is write our custom security
filter okay because our requirement is
different right so we have to write our
custom security filter we can do that we
have to add it into the chain okay that
is the first part we have to write
create our custom security filter and
add it into the filter chain. This
security filter has to create a custom
authentication object. Now you one thing
should have come to your mind that okay
Shange if I am creating a custom
authentication
object what authentic what
authentication provider will support
this because DAO authentication provider
does understand custom authentication
object no it can handle username
password token authentication object it
can only support this there might be
some other provider they support
different so we have to write our custom
authentication provider which understand
our custom
authentication
object. Okay. So we have to write our
own authentication provider. So we have
added the functionality here also.
Another thing is that this provider
which we have written newly we have to
update the list. We have to add it into
the list of the provider manager. Okay.
So that it will iterate over the list
over the authentication provider. Let's
say that it has four authentication
provider one DAO one different okay so
it will when I am getting a custom
authentication object it will first
check for DAO or for other and then
let's say that custom authentication
provider comes in it will call it
support method hey can you support this
custom authentication object it will say
yes and then it will delegate the to our
provider so we have to add our custom
filter into and once the custom filter
is added into the
chain, right? It has to create an object
of custom authentication object. Now
since the custom authentication object,
we have to write our custom
authentication provider which understand
this object.
Okay. And also update the authentication
manager this provider list. So it
maintains a list, right? So we have to
update it. Now the authentication
manager will get this object. It will
iterate over the list and calls the
support method. Okay. So it will pass it
to the custom authentication provider
only because it support method only will
return
true. So now we are getting some hint
that how we can implement the JWT
functionality using the security
framework itself. So can we start now?
Let's we can code for token generation
part. Okay. And don't worry I have
already pushed this code to the git. I
will share the link in the member
community section. I will share the link
or the git
link.
Okay. First first thing first we need to
add the JWT dependencies. Why we need a
JWT dependency? Because we need to have
an implementation which can generate
tokens. Right? So first is this J JJWT
API. So this is provide an API only.
Okay, we need an its implementation.
Either you can use the same JJWT
implementation or some other different
implementation. I'm using its uh
implementation only. Okay. So JJWT impl
its
implementation. Its uh interfaces
implementation API implementation. And
the third dependency you needed is JJWT
Jackson. It is required for JSON
processing. So in the payload you have
like key value key value key value.
Right? So this is nothing but in a JSON
form. So it has to parse it and take out
the particular data. So it need a JSON
processing capability. So we have to add
that also. And with this two it it signs
the key, it generate a token. So all
those functionality present here we will
see
that.
Okay. So now let's start it. So we have
added the
dependency. So this is the first filter
which we have to create JWT
authentication filter. So what we are
trying to achieve
now we have to create a token. We have
to generate token
right and when we have to generate a
token what we are implementing it we
have to expose an API let's say generate
hyphen token where user can pass its
username password okay what it will do
is it will
validate the username and
password whatever the data has already
present into the DB. It will validate
it. If it is match, we have to return
the JWT token. This is the functionality
we are trying to build. Okay. So, first
thing which we have added is the
filter. So, this filter what it does.
Now, see one by one whenever I created a
filter, I extended with one per request
filter. Okay.
Why? What does one per request filter
do? So we have a filter chain, right?
There are so many filters inside a
filter chain. So one per request filter
make sure
that in one request in one
request any filter should not run
twice. Okay. So any filter should run
only once per request. Okay. So that
what it makes sure that because sometime
what happen is this filter invoked this
this filter invoke this this filter
invoke this. So we need to internally it
need to make sure that what if it again
invokes
this. Okay. So it has to make sure that
no filter get invoked twice. So that is
just its functionality. That's why we
have extend our filter with the one per
request filter. Okay. So we are creating
our first
filter and uh we have to implement do
filter uh filter internal which is the
we have to provide it the implementation
of it. So here see that what I am
doing I am looking if the path of the
API is slash generate token then only go
ahead otherwise move to the next filter
like this filter will only
work when the path is generate token.
Okay. So we have to specify because we
are writing a new filter, right? We have
to make sure that it only process the
request which is intend to. So that's
where it is doing. So if if you're doing
form form based login, form based
authentication, if you see it, it will
check if it is login, then
only go and do some logic otherwise go
to the next filter. Maybe some other
filter might be interested in this
endpoint. Okay, so that's what here I'm
doing. If the endpoint is generate
token, then only this logic should run
otherwise move ahead with the next
filter. Okay, and return it from this.
Now, yes, user is calling the generate
token endpoint. Okay. So in the generate
token endpoint we have to pass uh
provide a you can object where user can
pass username password. So that's why
I'm creating a login request object. So
here user can pass username and password
in the body. Okay. Login request. So now
this endpoint is invoked. Yes. And this
filter yes match. And then it proceed to
work this. So what it will do is it will
read the login request first. The login
request has username password. What user
has passed here? Username
password. Now I got the username
password. And here if you see that I am
creating a token. I told you the filter.
What filter first does is create an
authentication object. What
authentication object I'm creating?
Username password authentication token.
you something might hit your mind as of
now. Hey Shanch, isn't this thing the
form based also using? Yes. So if you
see in username, password filter which
is used by form
based it create the same thing username
password token authentication token.
This is the same token which it
creates. Okay. And which provider can
handle this token? DAO authentication
provider. This DAO authentication
provider support
this username password authentication
token. So you can see that also. So if
you open
DAO it parent is this one is this has
something called support. Yeah. So this
username password authentication token
is supported by DAO. Okay. that we know
that. So you can ask me that hey then
why you are
creating this authentication token will
not the authentication manager pass this
your request to the DAO yes that's what
we wanted because what does DAO
does we have seen that right what DAO
does DAO authentication provider
whatever the username password comes in
first it will create a hash of the
password then based on the username it
will load the data either from the DB or
from inmemory we currently we are
storing into the DB so it will load it
from the DB then it will match it and it
will create the fully authentication
object and return so this authentication
has like fully authenticated true or
false that's what we wanted to do right
that's what we wanted to do once we get
the username password we have to
validate the username password so first
we have to hash it then based on the
username we have to load the data from
the DB whatever the username password is
stored then we have to match it and once
the matching is happened then only we
have to create a JWT token but all this
matching logic is already there in the
DAO provider so that's what I am using
that only so I created this token
intentionally and I pass the username
password okay so and after that I am
calling this authentication manager
authenticate and pass this token
authentication token to that. Then now
you know that what would happen this
authentication manager if you go the
framework authentication manager will
iterate over the providers okay it will
check the support hey who supports this
username password authentication token
the DAO will say that yes I will support
and it's will call its authenticate it
will do a proper matching and returns
ultimately okay and once we get the
authentication result. Okay. So since
this username password authentication
token is a child of authentication only.
So we can catch it into the parent. No
issues. So once it is authenticated what
we have to do we have to generate the
token and return. That's what I'm doing.
I am I have written one util. I am
calling that generate
token. Right? And uh once the token is
generated I am sending it to the
response header authorization beer this
one. Okay we will see that but you
understand the filter what it is doing.
So first filter part is clear right?
Request goes to
filter. Filter creates an authentication
object. Okay. Then it reach to the
provider.
provider passes to one of the
authentication uh uh this provider
manager you can say that authentication
manager authentication manager pass it
to authentication provider in this case
DAO provider got invoke it passes the
request with authentication equals to
true passes to the filter this filter
whatever we have written this now it
will generate the
token generate the
token and put it into the response
header. Okay. And do we need to iterate
to the next filter after this? No. After
this, we don't have to iterate to the
next filter because we have sent the
response. We don't have to go to the
controller level here at this point of
time. Do we need to go to the controller
level? No. So that's why I haven't do
filter chain. Do filter here. I don't
want to go to the controller. Just
return it from here.
So if this is clear we will see few
things like yeah login request we have
already seen that I have created this so
that uh user can pass the username and
password into the
request. Then here I have created JWT
utility utility
class. So if you see this is the method
which I have written where I am calling
generate token. Okay I am passing
whatever I have to put into my payload.
Right. and I want an expiry time of 15
minutes. Okay, so that's what generate
token what is the username and expiry
time. So this is the API and
implementation which we have added into
the pom right. So they have exposed this
APIs here what I am doing is I am using
in the dependency we have added u JJW
implaces right API. So we are using that
only to create the token. So we are
putting the subject issued at
expiration whatever the signing
algorithm which we have to use we are
putting it. Okay. So we have provided
like what is our key which we have to
use. Okay. And the algorithm which we
have to use to sign. Okay. So since we
are using HMAC which is a symmetric key
means the same key is used to encrypt
and decrypt. You can say that. Okay. So
the same key is used to sign and verify
in this case. Okay. So this is your
secret key which should not be stored
like this. This is just for demo
purpose. I am putting it to static final
but show it should be stored somewhere
like which cannot be accessed so easily.
Okay. So we have our secret key and we
use that
key and we will sign we will use this
algorithm to sign our payload. Okay. So
that is the
second thing we have which we have done
JWT implementation. Apart from that what
we have done is in the security config
if you see the security
config this see the red boxes we have
written this newly. Now see that in
security filter
chain this is the first thing which we
have added we have to create an object
of this our filter JWT authentication
filter right we have to create an object
of it see this is not add the rate
component spring will not create its
bean automatically we have to uh tell
okay because it's a filter so that's
where inside here in the bean here in
the bean
configuration we are creating its
object. We are creating new JWT
authentication filter. We are passing
the manager and JWT
util. Right? Why we are passing it
authentication manager and util? Because
it needed it. I have to generate a
token. So I need a JWT util object.
Right? I have this. It has to invoke
this. So that's why I need JWT util
object. And also I need to call the
authentication u to the authentication
manager method. Right? So I need
authentication manager object also. So
that's why I have this two
variables. So this security config
filter chain is passing the
authentication manager and JWT util to
it. Now before going to net yes we have
to create an object of authentication
manager and JWT util also. So see this
first I am creating a authentication
manager. There are two ways.
First way is you create your new
authentication manager. A provider
manager is the implementation.
Right? So here I am creating a new
provider manager and see I am giving my
own list of providers where it will
iterate over it. So currently I have
added only one authentication provider
DAO authentication provider. Remember
that spring boot do not automatically
adds any provider. Okay. If we are
creating a new provider manager, we have
to tell what all the providers we have
to put authentication providers we have
to put into the list. So I want only one
DAO authentication provider. You know
right? Because my filter whatever the
token I have created I know that DAO
authentication provider can handle it. I
have added it. The second way is
that get the authentication manager
object and update the update the list of
authentication provider instead of
creating new provider manager get
whatever the object is spring boot
already created and update its list.
Okay. But for now we can do anything.
Both are simple. Uh but for now I am
using that I am creating my new provider
manager and I have provided specifically
this
list. Okay. So authentication manager we
have created
it. Now JWT util. So here if you see
that JWT
util is nothing but add the rate
component. So object would be created by
a spring boot only. So we are just using
that and putting it here initializing it
here. Okay. So I am not creating new JWT
util. No uh because it has add the rate
component. So it object would be created
and it would get initialized at this
point of time. So now I have this two
objects. My authentication filter object
is
created. Now what I have done extra into
the security filter chain. Now I have to
see that whatever the filter you have
created I told you whatever the filter
you have created you have to add it into
the filter chain I have created the
filter but will it get automatically
added into the filter chain no we have
to tell we have to add it into this
chain and we have to tell the exact
place where we have to
add spring boot doesn't know
automatically where you have to put so
that's what I'm telling I'm telling add
filter before. So this is the filter
which I have created
newly. I have to add it before this
filter username, password authentication
filter. So you know that by default so
many filters got added. I think first
one is security context holder filter.
Second one is username password
authentication filter. Third one is
basic authentication filter. I think
fourth one is authorization filter. So
many filters are there. So now what uh
this does JWT authentication filter JWT
authentication filter where it will get
added into this list? We are telling add
filter before this is the filter add
before username password authentication.
So add before this. So this is the place
I'm telling add my filter
here. Got it? So this is also done.
Now one more thing this DAO
authentication provider right we have to
create its object as I told you that
automatically spring boot do not creates
authentication provider for us okay we
have to tell like what all providers we
want to use but you can ask that hey in
the previous form based authentication
basic authentication we haven't created
this right if you remember we were using
here something uh called
Right.
HTTP dot
form I think something called
customize.default something for basic
http.basic
customize.default. So this internally it
creates a lot of default functionality
for form and base. So they create an
object like what all providers they
might require. So they create an object
of it. they create a object and put it
into the list. But now here if you are
seeing we are not using HTTP basic we
are not using HTTP form right and we are
not using customize dotdefault. So
whatever is required we have to tell so
authentication manager object we are
creating it and we are telling that hey
we need only one authentication provider
as of now this is the
provider. Okay. So DAO authentication
provider needed this two thing password
encoder and user detail service because
we know that it has
to call the password encoder and call
the user detail service. So these two
things we have to set it and that's what
I have set it
here. Okay. password encoder which we
have already has the object at part of
at the time of user creation and user
details service user detail service also
add the red component we have determined
while creating the user so we are just
initializing it and that's all so our
security config is complete so what we
have done till
now we have created a filter we have
created a
filter we have put it into one of the
filter chain. There are lot of filters.
This is our filter. We have put it into
the filter
chain. We have provider manager and we
have uh have its list ready which has
DAO authentication
provider. Then we have some
authentication provider created. We have
created its object which is DAO
authentication
provider. Okay. So this all we have
done. Now what would happen? First is
user registered. The first thing we have
already exposed the API. User is
registering. SJ1 123 ro user in DB user
is registered. SJ 1 2 3 its role is
user. This would get created into the
DB. Now I am calling generate token API.
Okay. Now this generate token I am into
the body I am putting username password.
So this username password is getting by
this one login request username
password. Now I am hitting it. Now I am
hitting it. So what would happen? The
filter chain pass it to the
filter. Which filter it will get caught
is our
JWT authentication
filter. JWT authentication filter will
come. Okay. Because we have already
added into a specific place. We have
added into after uh before the uh
username password authentication filter.
So it will get invoked.
Now this will get invoked. This will
check hey generate token. Yes, this is
something I'm interested in. It will
take out a username login request.
Username password. It will create the
token and it will pass the
authentication manager. All right.
Authentication manager also we have
created which has only list of one
authentication provider which is DAO.
So that framework this is the framework
will ultimately get invoked. So it will
iterate over this provider only one
provider is there support it will call
DA1. Yes DAO supports username password
authentication token and ultimately it
will call its
authenticate. Okay. So DAO ultimately
will call password encoder call user
detail service which will load from the
DB match it ultimately return it to our
filter and then our filter calls JWT
util generate a token and put into
header authorization
beer. So here ultimately it will put
into authorization bearer and this is
our
token got
added. So token is generated at this
point of time. So here if you see that
we haven't exposed any API we haven't
exposed this API into controller we have
added into the security filters itself
and from there only we handle it and
very much specifically we are working
with the framework itself weighth uh
going way apart from the
framework if you understand this right
token validation is just a piece of
cake okay So now here in the token
validation what we have to do understand
that one now user is trying to access
any API let's say users API this is a
restricted API okay now it will pass JWT
token to us JWT token now we have to
validate this token validate token and
if token is validated so this is your uh
filter uh security framework
If the token is validated, it has to
pass it to the
controller. Controller, it will fetch
the resource and ultimately
return. Okay. So that's what we have to
do in inside a token validation. So here
if user try to access any restricted
resource, they need to pass the token
into the authentication header like
this. So whenever any request is coming
let's say API users user has to pass
like this in the authorization header
they have to choose beer token and pass
the token whatever we have written in
the previous step.
Okay. Now first thing first we have to
write our
filter. We have to write our filter
which will do this validation.
So I have created this filter again once
per request filter I have extended it.
Why? Because I need to make sure that
this filter only runs once per
request. So first thing I am doing no
matter what request. So here if you see
I'm not checking any users or anything.
No matter what request comes I am
extracting the JWT from the
request. I am extracting the JWT. How I
am extracting from the request? I am
reading the header authorization and it
starts with beer. So I'm take out the
token out of it. So I have taken out the
token. If token is not null, what I am
doing is I am creating a new
authentication object. Now you see that
I am creating a custom authentication
object. JWT authentication token. JWT
authentication token. It's a child of
abstract authentication token which is
again a child of authentication
object
authentication. So here if you see that
I am putting only one field token you
can even have more but I have only one
token.
Okay. Okay. Currently authenticated I
have set it to false. This is present
inside this. So currently it's
authenticated no and I have only one
token. So whatever the token which I
have get from the user. So what filter
does is filter first thing is that
create an authentication object. So I'm
creating JWT authentication token and I
have put this token whatever the u I'm
getting from the user. So I have put
here. So now I got a object but
currently it's authenticated
false authentication manager. I am
calling authentication manager dot
authenticate authentication token. Now
at this point of time you must ask a
question. Hey Shange the authentication
manager if you from the previous
generate token we have added only one
provider which is DAO and DAO
authentication provider do not
understand this. So who will access it?
Yes. So if you go to the security
config we have in the provider apart
from DAO we have added one more
authentication provider JWT
authentication provider. We have created
a new provider which understand this
authentication object. Okay. So we will
see that. So we have created a new
authentication
provider. New authentication provider.
So it's a child of authentication
provider. It support is yes I understand
JWT authentication token. So it
understand this JWT authentication
token. Okay. So authentication manager
calls the authenticate object. Now the
provider manager will iterate over the
list of authentication provider. So
there are two into the list. Right? So
it will first go to DAO. DAO do you
understand JWT
authentication object? it will say no I
don't understand then it will goes to
this hey JWT authentication provider do
you support this uh JWT authentication
token it will say yes I support it and
then it will call its
authentication
method so I'm calling it authenticate so
what this provider authenticating it now
you got this uh here right where it goes
it has to validate the token it has to
validate validate the token that's what
I am doing it here
now whatever the token I am getting
whatever from this
authentication I take out the token from
this authentication I take out the
token whatever the token I'm getting I
created one more method JW inside of JWT
util validate and extract username token
so here I am creating JWT this method we
have already created in generate and
this is I have created newly red one So
I am parsing the
JWT token. I have put the signing key
because it has since it's the HMAC right
so it has to use the same
key I am parsing it the claim the
payload part I am taking out its body
and from that body I taken out the
subject and subject I have put it the
username right and the subject I have
put it the username so I'm taking out
that extracting that
info I'm taking out that
username if username is null I am saying
invalid JWT token Right. But if I get
it, what I am doing it? I am calling
user detail service. Load user by
username. I am calling the DB fetching
the user detail service. It has let's
say username, password, role. Whatever
all the information about the user, I
got
it. Here you can say that this one
either you can enhance your uh JWT
authentication token itself, right? or I
am using username password
authentication token where I'm putting
this whole username details right and
ultimately returning
it because we have to do what we have to
do is here if you see we have to pass it
to the
controller right so from this filter we
have to we we don't have to return it
from here itself we have to let the
chain go and let it go through
controller and controller also should
have access to authentication
object. Okay, it has access to
authentication object. So that's what I
am trying to do here. So once it is
authenticated, token is valid. I am
creating a au because I have to return
an authentication object. Either you can
extend this itself. This is also an
authentication object. So currently I
have only token here. Okay. So you can
also create here uh JWT
authentication token itself. Okay. And
you can now change its authentication to
true at this point of time
authentication to true and also have a
placeholder which is stored this user
details which holds this user details.
So for simplicity purpose I haven't
extend all this information. So I uses
the uh existing authentication object
username password. I put the user
details here. Okay, it will
automatically make it to authenticated
true. It will return it to my
filter. Now if it is authenticated, I am
storing into the security context
holder. Now since it is stored in
security context holder, even the
controller have now access to it. Even
the controller now have access to it.
Now all I have to do is filter chain
dodo filter. I don't have to stop the
chaining.
continue. After this filter, my
validation is done. If authentication is
true, I put it into the security context
holder and go next. So maybe further
more filters after that filters
ultimately controller will get invoked
and once controller done it will return
the data what is asked
for. Okay. So first thing we we have
done is return an authentication filter.
Okay.
You understand that this is the second
thing which I have a custom
authentication object token.
Okay, this is the third because uh since
this is a custom authentication token, I
have to write a provider which
understand this. So I have a provider
which supports this and I have written
validate token. So this task is to just
validate it. If it is uh validated true
properly, I just load the user details
and put it into the authentication
object either the one which we have
created. For now, I have used the
existing one but we can use the what we
have created. We just need to expand
user details so that we can store it.
After that uh it will go back to the
filter but filter have store this
authenticate object into the security
context so that controller have access
to it also if required and after that
I'll let it go the chain so maybe
further chaining after security filters
ultimately control goes to
controller so JWT util we know that we
have added this method to
validated and in the security config see
that we already have this for
authentication I have added it I have
created an object of JWT validation
filter this filter which we have created
right so this is again a uh filter no
add the rate component so we have to
create an object of it so that's why I'm
creating an object of it new filter and
it required only authentication manager
object so that's why I'm passing this
authentication manager because it need
only
this okay and
uh yes so that's what this one I already
told you now this filter which we have
created we have to put it into some
space into the filter chain right so I
am adding this filter after after this
JWT authentication filter so this is my
validation filter I am adding it after
this JWT authentication filter so my
first is let's say some security context
holder filter by default. Second I have
put is
JWT authentication
filter and after that it was username
password authentication filter and now I
am putting validation filter after this
authentication filter JWT validation
filter. So I'm specifying its place
after
this. Okay. And uh so I have created a
filter and in the manager I have added
that hey this is the provider I also
need to add
uh and what else yes for this provider
you need to create an object because
this is the authentication provider at
the rate component is not there because
this is the wall framework
authentication provider child of this
one right so I'm creating authentication
provider object it required JWT user and
user data service so I'm passing it so
Everything is almost similar to what we
have done
previously in the generate token. So
clear this part how validation is done
and we have used the complete framework
itself. So again I am registering a
user. I got into the DV. Okay. SJ1 23
RO user. I am generating a token right
passing a username password. What would
happen
is our authentication filter will catch
DAO provider will use it to compare the
username password. Ultimately filter
will generate a token and return into
the authorization
header. Now I'm trying to access any
restricted resource. I have to pass this
token into this authorization beer token
and pass this. Okay. Now what would
happen is our filter get
invoked. Filter get invoked. We have
taken the token out of the header
authorization. We have created a new
authentication object pass to the pro uh
authentication manager. Authentication
manager will call to our provider.
provider will validate it and uh first
it will support yes and then it will
pass it and then it will validate it and
it will put into the uh security context
and filter do filter after all the
filters it will goes to our controller
controller will
yes fetch data successfully and
return okay so controller logic is a
business logic it has to fetch the user
but yeah I just system outprint and
something fetch user
successfully. Okay. But got it. How I am
doing the valid validate? If you pass
try to pass the invalid token, I pass
like hyphen invalid. This is not a valid
token, right? I'm passing invalid. So
here if you see it say forbidden
authentication got
failed. Okay. The control didn't reach
till the controller. It itself will fail
it. Okay. So
this validate and extract username.
Okay. So this will
fail it will say bad credential
exception. It will throw this exception.
Invalid JWT token bad credential
exception. Ultimately the request will
fail. The it do filter will not chain
ring will not happen. Controller till
controller it will not
reach. Okay. Now another thing come is
refresh token. We have to refresh
it. Generally access tokens are
shortlived. Okay. Like 5 minutes. In our
case we are creating a token for 15
minutes. Right here if you see that we
are creating a
token. Uh where is JWT util? Yeah. So
expiry minute. While creating a token we
provided 15. So for 15 minutes we are
creating a token. So just think from a
shoe of a user that hey after 15 minutes
I again have to provide a username
password and one thing also question
comes to that why only for 15 minutes
why can't we have it for 1 day 2 day 10
days so for security purpose so you know
that in from the previous
video the thing is with the token if it
get
leaked there is no way you can
invalidate the token before its expiry
so that's why it is always recommended
that the access token should be
shortlived. Okay. And since it is
shortlived, let's say 5 minutes, do we
required our customers after 5 minutes
you again put username, password? That
is not feasible. So that's where refresh
tokens come into the
picture. So access token get expired.
Then refresh token which is generally
long lived most probably 5 days 7 days 2
days okay is used to get new access
token without requiring username and
password okay then all we have to do is
keep the refresh token safe that's
all okay so we will see that how again
first thing first we are creating
a filter but
yeah now see the frame
First
thing when generating a
token again I'm going back to the first
API generate hyphen token. Okay what it
was doing is it will validate from DB if
matches it will generate the token. Now
it will again have to pass one more
refresh token two things. So one token
access
token second is refresh
token. Okay. So that is the first thing
I'm doing it. So in the existing JWT
authentication filter this red box
right. So first one we have already
created a token for 15 minute which is
an access token. I am putting into
authorization beer. Okay. I am putting
into authorization beer. Refresh token.
I am creating again the same JWT util
generate token. I am creating one more
token but creating it for 7
days. Creating it for 7 days.
Okay. And since this is a refresh token,
I am not putting into an header. I am
putting into a cookie. So see there are
two
ways. First way is that you return this
refresh token in response
body. Okay. So that client has two
onuses on the client to store it locally
store it or in memory. Okay. Another is
use a cookie and in the cookie we have
something let's say HTTP only it prevent
JavaScript from accessing it. I think in
front end uh JavaScript there is
something called document something
right through which we can access the
cookies with if set HTTP only set to
true you can't do it okay and also you
can put set secure equals to true means
it would be sent only over
HTTPS okay and we can also send that set
path means only when this API is hit /
refresh-en token okay then only cookie
available
for the refresh
endpoint. This cookie whatever we are
putting into the cookie generally it is
stored in the browser and browser will
send it for all the request generally
it's a cookie right so we are making
sure that hey browser only send it when
this path is hit / refresh token don't
add it otherwise for all the requests so
with this three things we can make our
refresh token
secure we don't allow access it we are
not storing it somewhere in local
otherwise if you are sending in the body
then client has to store it somewhere.
So we are not storing it we are keeping
it into the browser only uh we are we
are not allowing JavaScript to access
it. We are allowing it over HTTPS and
browser will only add this refresh token
when refresh token endpoint is hit. Okay
but this is just one way of
implementation based on your application
usage. You can change the uh how you
want to send back the refresh token that
depend but this is just my opinion how
it should
be. Okay. So the first I am done is that
during the generate token I have also
put a logic to return the refresh token
also. Okay. You can also ask one
question that hey why for access token
we are not putting into like cookie and
all this things is it not uh safe is it
our access token is not vulnerable it is
actually but here if you see that's why
we call it that it is a short live so
generally 5 minutes only for 6 minutes
it is valid so since it is for
shortlived the risk is very less okay
but since uh refresh cookies uh refresh
tokens are long live that's why we have
to secure it very well. Okay, but this
is a vast topic. You can say that is it
still a secure or not. But yeah,
different application, different
requirement, different way to return it.
But the core thing here is with generate
token, we have to return the refresh
token also that we have done it. So this
is the first thing we have done
it. Second thing I am writing my own
refresh filter. Now once this happened,
now let's say the token got expired. Now
user has to refresh it. So it will
call refresh token
endpoint. Okay. And I have to validate
the refresh token. And if it is validate
I need to generate a new access
token. So I have created a new filter
JWT refresh filter. Again a child of one
per request filter. I want to make it
run only one time.
So
here see that I am only interested when
this endpoint is hit. If any other
endpoint is hit, this filter has nothing
to do with it. Go ahead for the next
filters. Yeah, if this endpoint is hit,
refresh token proceed further. So what
I'm doing first extracting the JWT from
the request. Okay. So, user has passed
the refresh token in
the header, right? So, I have to take
out this extract it. So, I am extracting
it. Uh, so this it is not passed into
the header. It is passed into the
cookie. Refresh token we have discussed,
right? It is passed into the cookie. So,
I'm reading the cookie from there. I am
taking out the refresh token field. So
that's what we put right in the cookie
refresh token field and this token would
only be available when this endpoint is
hit refresh token. So this I'm hitting
this
uh querying this key so that I can get a
value. I got a refresh
token. I once you got a refresh token
what is the next step which filter does?
It creates an authentication object. Now
what this refresh filter has to do?
Refresh filter has to do validate the
token. And if you remember
that we have one already provider which
does the validation. So I am creating a
JWT authentication
token right what we have seen in the
second I think third step right like
where we are validating the token. So
the same authentication object I'm using
I just set the refresh token here and I
pass the authentication manager
authenticate. So now in the
authentication manager here if you
see authentication manager I still have
the two provider only DAO authentication
provider and JWT authentication
provider. So JWT authentication provider
will take care of it because it knows
how to handle JWT authentication token.
So this is the provider. So here if you
see we are already we are not doing
anything. It's all existing code which
we have seen in the pro uh previous uh
step. So it get the token whether it's
access token, refresh token, it doesn't
care. It just get a token and it will
validate it. And once it it validated,
it fs the user details and return the
fully authenticated object. So instead
of this place we can extend our uh
authentication token itself JWT
authentication token to store the user
details itself. But for now let's say
I'm using this authentication token but
no code this all we have done previously
in the previous step. So I'm using the
same token and call this. So ultimately
this provider will get invoked. It will
say that yes I support this token. It
will validate it and
returns. Now if it is authenticated
means refresh token is valid. Refresh
token is valid. What we have to do is we
have to generate a token. So I'm calling
JWT util generate token for 15 minutes.
It is valid. Expiry time is 15 minute.
I'm putting a header authorization beer
and added this
token. Do I have to do filter 10? Do I
have to rest still controller? No, I
don't have to rest controller. That's
why I
put I didn't put do filter
here.
Okay, I will return it from here itself.
So filter chain is also we created uh
refresh filter also we created provider
we reuse it we didn't create anything uh
JWT authentication token we reused
it JWT util we reused it generate and
validate already
there and here if you see in the
security config what we have written
newly is this we have to create our
filter object of it so we have created
an object And we have to put this filter
into the chain. I am putting add filter
after I am putting this filter new
filter after this validation
filter. Okay. Rest is all what we have
done. So if you see that first I am
registering the user in DB I got the
data. Second I am generating the token.
Authentication filter will get invoked.
It will call DAO authentication provider
validate it and ultimately generate now
this see access token and in the cookie
refresh token. I got
it. Now I am calling refresh token. What
would happen is this endpoint will get
invoked. Which endpoint? This one.
Refresh filter get invoked and this will
say that yes ultimately it go
next. it will validate it and if it is
validated it will generate a token
uh into the header response like this.
So this is the new token it will
generate and in the refresh token which
we have to pass it is automatically
coming from the cookie what we have in
this cookie
right ey.
So that will automatically pass in this
one request refresh token and our filter
will read from the cookie validate it
and generate a token in the header
authorization beer. Okay. And this is
very important to make it
secure. So the whole code is there in
the git link. I will share in the member
community section. So you can check the
git link and but I think this would be
totally clear right now. And the last
part is authorization. It is very very
similar to what form and basic
authentication we have done very simple
just see this let's say for this
endpoint I need to have a role user
that's all I have added this dot request
matchers whatever the endpoint whatever
the role you want it okay so now here if
you see I am creating a user and with
the role admin so in DB I have sj 1 2 3
and the role is
admin I have created create a token with
this username I get one
token now I'm trying to access a user
API what would happen is uh I'm passing
this token whatever I have get into the
authorization header BR token I got
forbidden why because this API required
role user but this has admin so mismatch
happened so there is something called
authorization filter comes into the
picture which we have already seen
in the form and basic
authentication authorization filter will
come into the picture, right? And uh it
will throw this
exception. So control will not reach
till controller
itself. Okay guys, so please go through
it again if you find it very lengthy and
uh little confusing because this is very
very important topic. All we are using
is framework. this part, this pink part
only we are writing actually. Okay.
So if you have any doubt, let me know.
We can discuss further in the comment
section. But I hope this video would be
helpful. Uh thank you guys. Bye.